On the 3rd of September 2017, the North Korean
military detonated a nuclear weapon underground,
one that was approximately ten times stronger
than any previous North Korean nuclear weapon.
The bomb was so strong the detonation
of it caused a 6.3 magnitude earthquake.
The nuclear test was one of several incendiary
actions taken by the North Korean dictator,
Kim Jong Un, in 2017 and 2018 to demonstrate
his power at home and abroad. Who is this
North Korean dictator and how much of a
threat does he pose to the safety of East
Asia? This is the story of Kim Jong Un,
the third ruler of North Korea.
The man known to history as Kim Jong Un
is officially said to have been born on
the 8th of January 1982, presumably in
the city of Pyongyang in North Korea.
There is no certainty about this though.
International intelligence services argue
that it is more likely that he was born in
January 1983 or January 1984. For instance,
when he studied abroad in Switzerland
as a young man, his passport gave his
birthdate as 1984. It is believed that the
year 1982 was symbolically chosen because
it correlated closely with the seventieth
anniversary of his grandfather’s birth.
Kim’s father was Kim Jong ll. He was the son
of Kim Il Sung, the leader of North Korea,
officially known as the Democratic People’s
Republic of Korea. Il Sung became the Supreme
Leader of communist North Korea, backed by
the Soviet Union and the Chinese Communists,
directly after the end of the Second World
War. He would rule North Korea as its absolute
dictator down to his death in 1994, when he was
succeeded by Kim’s father, Kim Jong Il. Hence,
over three dynasties the Kim family have ruled
North Korea with an iron grip since the end of the
Second World War. However, the nature of the state
and its foreign relations have changed over time.
Kim’s father had overlapping wives between the
late 1970s and early 2000s. Song Hye-rim was his
eldest wife. Ko Yong Hui was his second wife, a
former dancer who later became the de-facto first
lady of North Korea. Kim Jong Un was born from
this second marriage. He is known to have two full
biological siblings, an older brother who plays
no role in the country’s politics, and a younger
sister, Kim Yo Jong who plays a considerable role
in the regime. Then there are many half-siblings,
one of whom Kim Jong Un has famously clashed with.
There may be other illegitimate siblings. Given
the secretive nature of North Korean society,
it is difficult to be sure.
Kim was born into a relatively new country with a
paradoxically very ancient history. North Korea,
for instance, had only been established as a
separate country following the end of the Second
World War in the autumn of 1945. However,
the Korean peninsula is home to an ancient
culture that has made great contributions
to world history. For instance, some of the
most important innovations in paper production
and block printing were made in Korea in the
first millennium before being transmitted across
Eurasia to Europe in medieval times. Later, under
the Joseon Dynasty that ruled Korea between 1392
and 1910, Korea’s culture flourished, but it also
turned inwards as it became fearful of western
influences, especially the spread of Christianity.
Westerners began to refer to it as ‘The Hermit
Kingdom’ in the late nineteenth century. It was
conquered by Japan early in the twentieth century
and remained a core part of the Empire of Japan
until the end of the Second World War. Following
this it was divided along the 38th Parallel
between a Soviet-backed, communist North Korea
and a US-backed, pro-western South Korea.
In a way, North Korea continued to carry the
torch as a Hermit Kingdom after the war. Kim’s
grandfather had tried initially to unite Korea
under communist rule through the Korean War
between 1950 and 1953. Once that failed, North
Korea turned inwards, becoming a secretive and
authoritarian state. Where South Korea flourished
to become a modern and emerging technological
economy, albeit under its own dictators and
strongmen down to the 1980s, North Korea remained
backwards economically and cut off from much of
the world. Still, until the end of the Cold War,
North Korea had many allies and its economy
benefited from them. The situation would
change in the 1990s and 2000s as recent history
cast a considerable shadow over North Korea.
Although Kim was born in Pyongyang and was part of
the ruling family there, his earliest years, and
much of his life ever since, was cut off from the
day-to-day realities of ordinary North Koreans.
The family live in over a dozen plush palaces and
elaborate residences staffed and run by hundreds
or even thousands of staff and every whim of the
family was taken care of from Kim’s earliest days.
Unlike the people of their country, who generally
live in poverty, the Kim family was surrounded by
western technology and modern amenities. Kim’s
relationship with his mother was reportedly very
close, as was that with his sister, Kim Yo Jong.
The latter relationship has endured down to the
present day and she is one of the people closest
to her brother. Kim Yo Jong is even viewed as a
potential successor if Kim dies before his own
children come of age. His only known child Kim
Ju Ae has also been mooted as his potential
successor although as of 2026 she is thought
to be only 13 years old. As a young man, Kim’s
primary education took place at the Kumsusan
Palace of the Sun school in the capital, a school
for the elite of the North Korean regime, before
being sent to Switzerland. There he attended
the Liebefeld-Steinhölzli Schule under an alias,
Pak Un, though clearly many locals must have
found the strange entourage which surrounded
this ten or eleven-year old child in the town of
Bern to be peculiar. There he learned to speak
some English and German, and presumably a little
bit of French as well, though Kim has never been
known for his gifted educational abilities.
He returned to North Korea in around 2000 to
complete his secondary education. It was in
Switzerland where he seemingly developed a
fascination with basketball, a strange development
given that basketball is hardly that prestigious
in a country where football, skiing and other
sports are much more favoured. Back in North
Korea by the start of the twenty-first century,
Kim had to adjust to the new political climate in
the country. When he left for Europe years earlier
the country was undergoing a political transition.
His grandfather, Kim Il Sung, who had ruled for
nearly half a century, died on the 8th of July
1994. Kim Il Sung had ruled over a country that
was far from isolated on the world stage. He had
backers in Russia and China and a host of closes
allies amongst other communist rulers such as
Nicolae Ceausescu in Romania and even members
of the Non-Aligned Movement in the Cold War,
such as India. All of that had changed in
the early 1990s as the Cold War came to an
end and North Korea became isolated. This was a
development compounded by China’s economic market
liberalisation and efforts to move towards the
model of growth pursued by countries like Taiwan,
Singapore, South Korea and Hong Kong
between the 1950s and 1980s. As a result,
while Kim Jong Il’s succession had been planned
as early as 1980, it was unclear what approach
he would adopt as the new country’s leader.
In the end, Kim opted for continuing North Korea’s
isolationist approach and even deepened it,
seeking economic autonomy. In the short term this
was disastrous. The first five years of Kim Jong
Il’s time as leader were characterised by crisis
and famine. As the subsidies that North Korea had
relied on for years from Russia and other Cold War
allies dried up, food shortages abounded. Hundreds
of thousands tried to flee the country. Many more,
perhaps even millions, either starved to
death or experienced severe malnutrition.
If Kim Il Sung was guilty of developing an
authoritarian government with strong ties
to the Soviet Union and China, his son quickly
established himself as someone who had little
concern for the wellbeing of his own people. Kim
was away in Switzerland, but he must have been
aware of what was happening at home on some level.
Kim was a child when his father became Supreme
Leader of North Korea in 1994. He was also a child
of his second marriage and was not viewed as the
heir in waiting at this early point in affairs.
Instead, his older half-brother from Kim Jong Il’s
first marriage to Song Hye-rim, Kim Jong-nam was
believed to be the designated successor. Jong-nam
was born in 1971 and was consequently entering his
mid-twenties at the time that his father became
the new head of state. He had years to further
acclimatise to the position and was viewed in
some circles within North Korea as a relatively
shrewd individual. However, two major developments
occurred after Kim Jong Un returned to North Korea
from his studies in Switzerland which rapidly
changed the succession plans. Firstly, fear began
to grow that Jong-nam was a reformer of sorts who
was not dedicated to the Juche ideology of
the country. This is a political ideology
similar to Marxist-Leninist thought. It was
developed extensively in the writings of Kim Il
Sung throughout his long reign and elaborated on
further by his son and successor. Secondly, in the
summer of 2001, Kim Jong-nam was arrested in Japan
after travelling there with his family using fake
passports and under assumed aliases. The purpose
of the trip was to visit Disneyland in Tokyo.
This did not reflect well on his suitability as
a potential future leader of North Korea.
Owing to the poor judgement displayed by Kim
Jong-nam and the fact that Jong Un was now
entering his twenties and beginning to build
up his own faction of supporters at the North
Korean political court, a power struggle
emerged in Pyongyang during the 2000s.
Remember, Kim Jong Il was well into his
fifties when he succeeded his father. As such,
his reign was never going to be as long as that
of Kim Il Sung. It was therefore important for
the successor to position himself to take over
before Jong Il died. This was especially so
given that there were frequent rumours about their
father’s ill health, including one bizarre story
that he had died from diabetes in the early
2000s and was being represented on the world
stage by an impersonator. To cement his growing
claim to succeed his father, despite being a
much younger son, Jong Un married in 2009 and had
children. His wife was Ri Sol-ju. Little is known
about her background, upbringing or political
views, and perhaps that was the goal. Theirs is
a seemingly traditional, stable marriage that
has resulted in several children. In contrast,
Kim Jong-nam had several wives and mistresses,
many who have lived extensively in Macau and
Beijing in China over the years. Their connections
to foreign entities complicated the possibility
of Jong-nam succeeding even further.
Beyond his wife and family, Kim is known
for being a bit of an enigma. He has
been widely satirised in western media
on account of this and there are a lot of
genuinely quirky elements to his personality.
For instance, his love of cheese has allegedly
led to a complex system of importing cheeses from
around the world. He is famously scared of flying
and travels across large distances by train. He
has a strange fascination with western culture.
In Kim Jong Un’s case this manifested itself
around basketball and he is a keen fan of the NBA.
This is a peculiar family tendency. His father was
notorious for his massive collection of western
DVDs. Kim is also understood to potentially have
a large fondness for alcohol. Political meetings
can involve drinking strong spirits and rice wine.
What this means is that, even at a relatively
young age, Kim is possibly suffering from a
lot of health problems. He is clearly obese
and is also potentially suffering from gout.
These known particularities about him aside, there
is an awful lot about Kim that remains unknown
today to those outside of North Korea. From as
early as his older brother’s ill-fated Disneyworld
trip in 2001, Kim Jong Il was beginning to groom
Kim Jong Un as his new successor. Insiders within
the regime and defectors have stated that Jong Un
was simply viewed as being most like his father
in temperament and approach. Hence, at the end of
the 2000s Kim Jong Il began bringing his son into
government and giving him new responsibilities.
This clearly demonstrated to the powerful North
Korean military and other powerbrokers that
Jong Un was the new successor designate and
would follow his father as third Supreme Leader
of North Korea. They did not have long to wait for
this to become an eventuality. In 2009 Kim Jong
Un was officially announced as the successor.
Two years later, Kim Jong Il died at 70 years
of age on the 17th of December 2011.
The country that Kim took over in 2011 was facing
many challenges. On account of its strange history
and the development of its nuclear weapons system
under his father, the country was deeply isolated
on the world stage. It was also already under
crippling economic sanctions and there had
been a failure to revive the economy for the
most part. The situation had improved slightly
since the famine of the 1990s, but there were
continuing food shortages. It was also common for
electricity to simply be unavailable. Pyongyang
functioned reasonably well, as the capital. Yet
even there the power could go out for days
at a time. Further away from the capital it
was like living in the pre-modern world. In
the cities and towns there were industries,
though these were very much like early Soviet-era
facilities or those found in Germany at the start
of the twentieth century. The average salary
was the equivalent of less than $2,000 a year,
while the overall size of the economy was just $28
billion dollars. Compare this with South Korea.
Admittedly the population there was approximately
twice the size of North Korea’s, with some 50
million inhabitants in 2011. However, at slightly
less than two trillion dollars in overall value,
its economy was sixty times the size of North
Korea’s. Furthermore, what money North Korea had
was generally being expended on its military or a
highly corrupt political establishment. This would
allow Kim and his family to live in luxury.
Two things are worth bearing in mind when it comes
to Kim Jong Un and his regime. Firstly, there
is the manner in which he has relied on a small
number of key nations abroad for the regime to
remain buoyant economically and politically.
Today a lot of the international headlines are
generated by Kim’s alliance with Vladimir Putin,
a topic which we’ll return to shortly, but for
the very most part North Korea is a de-facto
province of the People’s Republic of China. China
accounts for about 90% of North Korea’s trade and
economic support and has done so since the end of
the Cold War. It also has ties to other countries
that are deemed to be pariah states within
the global world order such as Afghanistan,
Syria, Iran, Eritrea and Equatorial Guinea. In
short, under Kim, North Korea has displayed zero
interest in becoming a more acceptable member of
the international community. It is under heavy
sanctions and is one of the few countries
worldwide which refuses to sign dozens of
international treaties on human rights. Finally,
because of its huge reliance on China, Russia and
Iran, North Korea has no option but to go along
with whatever the foreign policy prerogatives of
those nations have been over time. As we will see
very shortly, this has dragged North Korea into
its first hot war in seventy years in Ukraine. The
Chinese premier, Xi Jinping, does not like it when
North Korea acts unilaterally to fire ballistic
missiles over Japanese airspace. The Chinese are,
above all, merchants. They want a stable system
in the Pacific that fosters trade and wealth. Kim
is often seen as a liability, in much the same
way Beijing is perhaps not delighted about how
destabilising Russia’s war in Ukraine has been for
the world order and trade in general.
There has been one notable effort made during
Kim’s 13+ years as head of North Korea to try
to reach a rapprochement with the western
world. This concerned negotiations between
Kim and the American President Donald Trump back
during his first term as US President. Trump has
many detractors and many supporters. Some of the
things he has been particularly anxious to break
ground around are in the realm of international
affairs. This has had some success when it came
to the Abraham Accords in the Middle East and
his recent brokering of a peace agreement between
Israel and Hamas in October 2025. When Trump first
entered office in 2017, tensions were extremely
high between North Korea and the west, especially
owing to the launching of missiles over Japanese
and South Korean airspace. Trump’s administration
organised a summit in Singapore with Kim in
mid-June 2018. This was the first meeting, after
seventy years since the division of the Korean
Peninsula, during which a US President had met
with a leader of North Korea. The summit met
with little tangible success. A second summit was
organised in Hanoi in Vietnam for the following
year, but ultimately this diplomacy had virtually
no tangible impact. Under President Joe Biden and
Trump’s second term no further progress has been
made towards rapprochement with Kim’s North Korea,
in large part because of his alliance with Russia
and distractions with other conflicts.
A huge element of Kim’s time as leader of North
Korea has been centred on the country’s nuclear
weapons programme. The regime had begun working
towards achieving nuclear power all the way back
in the dark days of the Cold War in the 1960s. In
the 1970s the Yongbyon Nuclear Research Centre was
set up with Soviet aid. This was meant to be
for the purposes of producing nuclear energy,
not weapons, at a time when Moscow was trying
to convince its allies to sign up to the Treaty
on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons.
With Soviet assistance cooling in the late
1970s and 1980s, the quest for a nuclear weapon
slowed and Kim’s grandfather appears to have
genuinely decided that co-operation with other
international parties was better than acquiring
a nuclear deterrent. It was really under Kim’s
father that North Korea went full speed ahead on
acquiring a nuclear weapon. It entered into talks
with the US and western nations about freezing
its programme in the post-Cold War world, while
simultaneously moving ahead clandestinely with
that same programme. In 2003 it officially
withdrew from the Non-Proliferation Treaty
and accelerated its drive to finish making a
weapon. The culmination of all this was that
the regime tested its first ever plutonium-type
nuclear weapon on the 9th of October 2006. The
yield was small. It was less than one kiloton.
To put this in perspective, the two bombs dropped
on Hiroshima and Nagasaki in 1945 were 15 and 21
kilotons. Regardless, North Korea had successfully
tested a nuclear weapon.
Kim’s time as leader of North Korea has involved
major expansion of the nuclear weapons programme.
The first known nuclear test during his rule,
North Korea’s third overall, was carried out
in 2013 and was a message to the international
community that he intended to continue where his
father had left off. Then came a swift fourth,
fifth and sixth test in quick succession in 2016
and 2017. The sixth was the most concerning. While
the previous tests had been gradually increasing
in strength up to roughly ten kilotons, the 2017
test was estimated to have been anywhere between
140 and 250 kilotons, roughly ten times more
powerful than the weapons dropped by the US on
Japan in 1945. This was deeply concerning for the
international community. A bomb this size would
not completely destroy a city as large as Seoul,
the capital of South Korea, but it would cause
devastating damage, killing hundreds of thousands
of people, perhaps even millions and creating
a nuclear half-life that would make the city
uninhabitable and lead to widespread death from
radiation poisoning as well in its aftermath.
Having tested this weapon, North Korea had proved
to the world that it was now an enormous threat
to its neighbours. On top of this Kim Jong
Un is the North Korean ruler who has really
ramped up the country’s drive towards building
more and more advanced ballistic missiles,
ones that can travel thousands of kilometres. In
theory, weapons like the Hwasong-15 and Hwasong-17
ICBMs could reach as far as the West Coast of the
US. They would be intercepted before they did,
yet the main point remains: if North Korea is
attacked it could quickly devastate South Korea
and potentially Japan too with its weapons.
It is reasonable to say that the North Koreans
are not stupid or crazy, though they might like
to appear unpredictable at times for the simple
reason that unpredictability is a weapon that
can be deployed in international diplomacy.
The reality is that Kim and his advisors have
developed these weapons and continue to carry out
tests because they ensure the continuation of the
regime. Simply put, western powers like the United
States are not attempting to try to overthrow
the North Korean regime. While interception
technology is getting better and better all the
time in the twenty-first century, if the North
Koreans fired off an Inter-Continental Ballistic
Missile fitted with a nuclear warhead at Seoul,
it would likely make it through and strike the
city, for the simple reason that it’s so close
to North Korea. Therefore, as much as Kim might
appear volatile, there is a strategic rationale
to what North Korea has done over the last twenty
years. Nobody is going to try to overthrow the
dictatorship here in the way that Saddam Hussein
was overthrown in 2003, or by the manner in
which the CIA and other foreign adversaries have
worked to undermine governments in many different
countries. North Korea’s nuclear deterrent
has therefore meant that Kim can act in ways
inaccessible to countries without nuclear weapons.
Take the example of the assassination of his older
brother, Kim Jong-nam. After he fell out of favour
and was removed from the succession in 2003,
Jong-nam was exiled from North Korea. In the
years that followed he moved around repeatedly.
For instance, he was in Macau for a long spell of
time and was said to have good relations with the
Chinese government. There were also inferences
that he was in contact with western governments.
It is believed that he was allowed to fly
back to North Korea for an extremely brief
visit to pay his respects when his father died
in 2011. Even though he repeatedly stated he had
no desire to return to North Korea after this
to try to displace his brother in the 2010s,
concerns continued surrounding
his actions in Pyongyang.
These were intensified by the publication
of a book entitled My Father, Kim Jong Il,
And Me by Jong-nam. Kim decided to act after
he determined that his brother was a lingering
threat abroad. In a bizarre incident, two women
approached Jong-nam in Kuala Lumpur International
Airport in Malaysia on the morning of the 13th
of February 2017 and threw a substance on him.
They believed they were taking part in
a prank game-show. In reality they had
applied a VX nerve agent on Jong-nam after being
instructed to do so by North Korean agents who
quickly flew out of Malaysia. He died within
20 minutes from the lethal contact. The two
women involved were eventually exonerated, as
they were not aware of what they were doing.
Kim Jong Un has never claimed responsibility
for the attack, but it was clearly the North
Koreans. It is hard to imagine a government
acting in such a clearly inflammatory way as
this on foreign soil without a sizable military
deterrent of the kind North Korea possesses.
It is the typical assumption for many people
that these human rights abuses in North Korea
are solely the result of Kim Jong Un and his iron
grip on power. Conversely, many people question
how powerful he really is, or how actively he
controls the government. Questions of this sort
were especially prevalent when he assumed power
as a young man. Stories focused on his obsession
with basketball, playing video games and apparent
fondness for alcohol to suggest that he might not
be as actively in control of North Korea as the
regime want the outside world to believe. To
analyse this, we need to look at the structure
of the regime and government in North Korea.
The state has been controlled at the very top
by the Kim family since the very foundation of
the country after the Second World War. Kim,
and his father and grandfather before him,
have all held the official title General Secretary
of the Worker’s Party of Korea. They have all
been leaders of the sole political party within
North Korea, which proclaims itself to still be
a communist party in line with its establishment
along communist lines after the Second World War.
The executive organ of the Worker’s Party is the
Politburo, a kind of government cabinet that has
ministers who, in theory, advise Kim and act
as heads of different government departments.
Like any country, no matter what kind of system
it operates under, there is an entire system of
national, regional and local government. No state
can operate without such a system. Therefore,
while Kim would appear to be the all-powerful
head of North Korea and this is how the regime
presents him, there is a functioning political
system and government apparatus in North Korea
at the same time.
Where the real question of the power structure
within North Korea arises is over the relative
power of the Korean People’s Army and the
generals at the top of it. Simply put, the North
Korean regime has survived by placing military
strength at the very core of its activity. If
North Korea did not have a large military and
a nuclear weapons system that poses a threat
to neighbours like South Korea and Japan,
the regime would probably not have survived. Yet,
like all dictatorships, the Kim family can only
remain in power so long as it retains control over
the military. If a dictator loses the support of
the military, he is usually finished. Accordingly,
some international observers have questioned
whether Kim Jong Un, who can, as we have
seen, come across as an immature and frivolous
individual in certain ways, is actually the real
power in North Korea or if a cohort of military
generals wield effective power while Kim remains
the figurehead of the regime. For instance,
Kim Yong Bok is an extremely powerful figure
within the North Korean military who appears
to wield an enormous amount of influence. He
rose steadily during the latter stages of the
rule of Kim Il Sung and throughout the rule of
Kim Jong Il. Under Jong Un he has become one of
the most powerful people in North Korea, sitting
on the Central Committee of the Worker’s Party,
holding the title of Colonel General in
the military and heading up several of the
elite units of the Korean People’s Army. Through
these it is estimated that he oversees hundreds
of thousands of military personnel. He has been
broadly in charge of the North Korean contribution
to Russia’s war in Ukraine and is regularly
photographed with Kim and during international
summits with allied leaders of the regime like
Vladimir Putin. Many observers question if
people like Yong Bok are the real power behind
the metaphorical throne in North Korea.
However, there is a lot of evidence to indicate
that Kim really is as wholly in control of the
regime as he outwardly seems. He has, for example,
ruthlessly demoted people when he thinks that they
have become too powerful, and on occasion these
individuals and generals have broadly disappeared
from public view. "This is what happened with
Ri Yong-ho in 2012 only a few months after Kim
came to power. Ri rose through the ranks of the
military under Kim's grandfather and father. He
became the army chief in the final years of
Kim Jong Il's rule. Just six months after Kim
Jong Un came to power, Ri was purged from
his positions. It is unclear to this day
if he was killed or what his fate was."This
has happened with many potential rivals for
power within North Korea. Nor does Kim simply
remove individuals and have them disappeared as
soon as he perceives them as a threat. There also
appears to be a pattern of demoting officials and
rotating them between offices. For instance, Pak
Thae-song rose under Kim Jong Il and continued to
earn promotion under Kim. He became Chairman
of the Supreme People’s Assembly in 2019,
but then promptly disappeared from
public appearances in 2021. However,
he has since re-emerged and has been made
the Premier of North Korea, a kind of head of
cabinet. Clearly what Kim is doing here is making
individuals reliant on him but also introducing
uncertainty into the lives and positions of any
potential rivals. Concurrently, he has promoted
allies who owe their positions exclusively to
him. There is a very strong argument that Kim
is fully in charge of North Korea.
One of the reasons why Kim’s control over
North Korea has been questioned is owing to some
of the more unusual events of his time in charge
of the country. Take the example of the visits
of Denis Rodman to North Korea over the years.
Rodman is one of the most famous and successful
basketball players of all time. He won five
NBA championships in the 1990s with the Detroit
Pistons, San Antonio Spurs and Chicago Bulls and
was considered to be one of the greatest players
of his era, second only to Michael Jordan. His
post-playing career has been less salubrious.
Rodman’s issues with alcohol and mental health
struggles are well-documented. They in part
explain his decision to visit North Korea on
several occasions to help train the North Korean
basketball team and indulge Kim’s passion for the
sport as his guest of honour there. During one
of these visits in 2014 Rodman was accompanied
by a large entourage and the entire embassy for a
documentary entitled Dennis Rodman’s Big Bang in
Pyongyang. The whole thing turned into something
of a dangerous debacle after Rodman appeared
visibly drunk and aggressive during several
state gatherings with North Korean officials and
verbally attacked the narrator of the documentary,
the Irish journalist Matt Cooper. The whole thing
did not exactly cast Kim and his nation in a
serious light. We see a washed-up and drunken
former sports-star as the bizarre guest of honour,
indulging Kim’s hobby in a country with virtually
no experience of any success in professional
or national basketball events. Incidents like
this are what make it so hard to decipher who
Kim is and what he is about as a leader.
The Rodman incident should not fool anyone at
the same time. North Korea has long been known
for its human rights abuses and the brutal way
it crushes political dissidents. Accurate figures
are hard to come by but there are clearly
hundreds of thousands of people either in
jail or internment camps in North Korea. The
jails are terrible places, rife with disease
and often resembling nineteenth-century
prisons from other parts of the world.
Slave labour is employed here to produce goods
that turn a profit for the regime. Torture is
prominent, and Kim sanctions it, though it should
be acknowledged that these are both longstanding
issues that preceded his time in power and that
people are filtered in and out regularly. Many
serve as ‘re-education’ camps used to suppress
any form of political dissent. They are part of
the wider oppressive system of state censorship
and the cult of the leader in North Korea. This
was built on the same fundamental principles as
the cult of leadership around Joseph Stalin and
Mao Zedong in Russia and China at the time when
North Korea came into existence.
Hundreds of huge statues of Kim, his father
and grandfather adorn public places around
the country and the state-run news agencies
typically refer to him as ‘Great Leader’,
‘Beloved Father of the People’ or even the
‘Genius of Creation and Construction’. It is also
almost impossible to escape the state censored
media. For instance, North Korea runs its own
internally controlled version of the World Wide
Web known as the Kwangmyong. There are virtually
no loopholes around it to find information from
the wider World Wide Web. Only high-level state
officials or a small number of tech-savvy hackers
living near the land border with China are able
to get access to the wider internet and its
huge traffic. Equally, telecommunications
are controlled by Kim’s government, with a
state-run network called Koryolink running
the mobile phone networks. Kim is the member
of the dynasty who has overseen all of this.
The need for such state censorship of this kind
was unnecessary in his grandfather’s time and
was only emerging as an issue in North Korea
towards the final years of his father’s rule.
Kim, to use a simple term, is the digital-age
dictator of the Kim dynasty in North Korea.
Kim’s position within North Korean society is
not all about brute-force authoritarianism and
a cult of leadership. A certain section of North
Korean society favours him because their lives had
improved during his time as ruler of the country
since late 2011. The 1990s and 2000s were tough
years for the regime. Conversely, there has been
decent economic growth in the 2010s and parts of
the 2020s. Elements of the kind of western market
liberalisation favoured by China and Vietnam,
two countries that claim to still be communist,
but which are clearly not, have been introduced.
Collectivised farms and factories are allowed
to reinvest their profits and workers are given
better pay and conditions based on performance.
The average North Korean still lives in poverty,
though not to the same extent as in the final
years of Kim’s grandfather’s rule or his father’s
seventeen-year reign. This is in stark contrast
to Kim himself and his wife and children, as well
as the upper brass of the government and military.
Kim is, for instance, a billionaire in real terms,
with many palaces, a fleet of luxury cars, trains,
and huge amounts of disposable assets and cash
reserves.
The family are always conscious of the possibility
of regime change, so billions of dollars in assets
are held by Kim and his closest allies in banks
in China and Southeast Asia. They also probably
hold assets in Swiss and Caribbean banks
through third parties and shell accounts,
though this is hard to prove. Beyond this, Kim
has operatives who engage in a labyrinthine array
of schemes to bring in money for himself, his
family and his allies. North Korea, for instance,
is now recognised as one of the biggest players
worldwide when it comes to cryptocurrency scams.
The benefit it enjoys in this area is that it is a
state rather than an individual. If an individual
cryptocurrency scam artist robs hundreds of
millions of dollars in crypto assets, they can
avoid detection for a while by moving to places
like Dubai, Myanmar, and the Philippines or even
somewhere like Serbia and Bulgaria in the Balkans.
However, they can eventually face extradition and
laws are tightening everywhere. North Korea is an
exception: a place where the ruler himself is the
scam artist. Some studies suggest the regime has
made several billion dollars in crypto-related
scams in recent years, much of which is
funnelled to Kim and his family and allies.
Kim, like all world leaders, had to oversee his
state’s management of the Covid-19 pandemic in
2020 and 2021. Global understanding of how the
pandemic played out in North Korea is limited.
The regime was slow to admit that the virus had
even entered the country or confirm its first
cases. The inference was that North Korea remained
miraculously free of the disease until well into
the pandemic, despite its proximity to China where
the pandemic originated late in 2019. In a way it
makes a lot of sense that North Korea would not
have had a lot of the virus circulating in its
country. It’s an isolated nation, with virtually
zero tourists or business travellers coming in and
out. Furthermore, its land borders are not exactly
porous. The southern border is a demilitarised
zone that a person can be shot for trying to cross
over. North Korea was consequently like an island
in the way that it could shut itself off from the
world and attempt a zero Covid strategy. And this
is how it tried to present matters, claiming
that the virus-free country was indicative
of the success of Kim’s leadership. In reality,
though, the disease was circulating in North Korea
earlier than most other countries. Although Kim’s
government did move extremely quickly to close its
borders and limit travel in January 2020, two
months before most of the rest of the world,
it was already present in cities like Sinuiju
where the country’s first death took place
in February 2020. Information about the disease
trajectory in North Korea was extremely limited.
In 2022, by which time the pandemic was dying
down worldwide, the country finally admitted
to the presence of it in the country and that
Kim himself had a fever. The country admits to
74 people having died from Covid-19. At the
same time, it stated that over four million
experienced what it called ‘fever’. If millions
of people experienced symptoms it is implausible
that only 74 could have died from it. Given the
known pathology of the virus, it is more plausible
that tens of thousands of people lost their
lives in North Korea during the pandemic.
The Covid-19 Pandemic led to a major
diplomatic incident between North and South Korea
in the summer of 2020, or at least it contributed
to it. The Korean War has never ended. A ceasefire
was declared back in July 1953 at the end of the
conflict and a demilitarized zone was set up along
the 38th Line of Latitude North of the Equator.
There have been a lot of flare ups here over the
decades, principally owing to North Koreans trying
to flee to the South. In the first years of Kim’s
rule, it appeared as though things were improving
here, despite the routine border skirmishes and
shootings of individuals trying to pass through
the demilitarized zone. However, a joint liaison
office had been built at Kaesong in an industrial
base here near the border. The Inter-Korean
Liaison Office, as it is formally known,
was built following a meeting in 2018 between
Kim and his South Korean counterpart at the time,
President Moon Jae-in. Unfortunately, despite
millions of US dollars being spent on erecting
the four-storey building, the office was closed
in late January 2020. It was then destroyed in a
controlled demolition on Kim’s orders on the
16th of June 2020. Covid had apparently put
peaceful reunification off the cards again.
Elsewhere, Kim has strengthened his few remaining
international alliances. North Korea has become
a direct ally of Vladimir Putin in his war with
Ukraine. That conflict has been underway in
one shape or another since February 2014 after
the Maidan Revolution in Ukraine overthrew a
pro-Russian leader. While the initial conflict
in 2014 involved Russian annexation of the
Crimean Peninsula and a localised war in the
Donbass region of eastern Ukraine, the war has
expanded since late February 2022. It has been
costly for Russia in terms of casualties suffered
and Putin is paying extremely large amounts of
money to Russians to get them to fight. In 2024
a new source of cheaper fighting men was found.
North Korea directly allied with Russia and
thousands of North Korean troops began arriving
across Eastern Europe to fight the Ukrainians
from October that year. Over 10,000 North
Koreans are believed to have fought in Ukraine
down to late 2025. These men earn far less than
their Russian counterparts and are often used as
cannon-fodder on the frontlines. Kim in return
has received hundreds of millions of US dollars in
funding from Putin in return for his assistance,
with hundreds of millions more flowing into North
Korea via soldiers’ wages and so forth. This is a
notable shift in international diplomacy too. It
is the first time that North Korea has deployed
troops extensively to aid an ally in a foreign war
since the armistice in the Korean War was agreed
in 1953. North Korea did provide some logistical
and material support to the North Vietnamese
during the long-running Vietnam War in the 1960s
and 1970s, but the deployment of North Korean
troops in Ukraine is far more extensive.
It is all too easy to belittle Kim Jong Un as
a peripheral player in a network of leaders
sometimes called the Axis of Evil in the western
media. The view is often of Kim bungling along
like a lackey next to figures like Vladimir
Putin and Xi Jinping when they meet in Beijing
and so forth. And yet this is not entirely the
case. On the 10th of October 2025 the North
Korean government held celebrations to mark the
80th anniversary of its movement after the end
of the Second World War. This involved firing
off a new Inter-Continental Ballistic Missile,
the Hwasong-20, the strongest ever launched by
North Korea. There is also mounting evidence of
the country’s efforts to develop AI capabilities
as part of its military arsenal and functions.
Like Iran, Russia and China, North Korea will
soon dwarf most western nations when it comes
to unmanned drone warfare technology. Those who
dismiss the North Korean regime under Kim as a
bit of a joke are misinformed. Their current
leader might be around for much longer than
we think. With a country that is beginning to
develop economically beyond the perilous years
of the 1990s and 2000s, it might well begin
to become a much more powerful player again
in the politics of the Far East in years to
come. This is especially so when we consider
the instability of South Korea’s politics in
recent times when compared with the North.
Kim Jong Un is a very strange leader. He has been
mocked and vilified for over a decade as North
Korea’s leader, viewed as a slightly comical
figure who only finds himself in a position of
power because of the circumstances of his birth.
Perhaps there is some truth to this. Intelligence
services worldwide believe that Kim was lucky in
gaining the position as the third Supreme Leader
of North Korea. Through the process of elimination
of other male candidates within the family as
potential successors, Kim was chosen to succeed
his father. Although international observers have
continued to wonder if he is little more than
a stooge for some of the more powerful elements
within the North Korean military and the long
entrenched political elite, there are more than
enough signs that Kim is actually well and truly
in control of this highly authoritarian regime.
He either eliminates rivals altogether or else
moves them around within the government in such
a way which limits their capacity to become
rivals for power. The assassination of his
own brother in such an audacious way demonstrates
his ruthlessness. Perhaps the most striking thing
of all is the way in which Kim has developed
North Korea into a country with one of the most
formidable nuclear and inter-continental ballistic
weapons programmes anywhere on Earth. Simply put,
nobody can remove him from power from abroad.
If the US or any other antagonist tried to do
something, Seoul would risk being devastated
by nuclear warheads, and perhaps Tokyo too.
No foreign power is likely to take that risk.
Moreover, through his alliances with China,
Iran and Russia, Kim has strong Asian
allies that ensure that the North Korean
economy can potentially grow as part of a
new emerging world order in the Far East.
Western governments might focus on his
peculiar obsessions with basketball,
his alleged fondness for alcohol and his
portrayal of himself as an idiot savant. But
presumably informed secret services in the
US, Britain, Australia, Japan, and South Korea
know they are dealing with a far more formidable
enemy than is often suggested in media circles.
Only time will tell what happens in North
Korea under a ruler who could remain in
power there for many decades to come.
Could you say ID-ee-owe SAV-ont
What do you think of Kim
Jong Un? Is he really the all-powerful absolutist
dictator of North Korea, or do you think the power
structure behind the scenes of this secretive
state is more complex than people often imagine?
Please let us know in the comment section, and in
the meantime, thank you very much for watching.